宇宙就是这样
The cosmos is all there is
过去是这样
or ever was,
以后还是这样
or ever will be
跟我来
Come with me.
30多年前
A generation ago,
宇航员卡尔·赛根站在这里
the astronomer Carl Sagan stood here
带领全世界数亿人
and launched hundreds of millions of us
进行了一场历险
on a great adventure...
用科学去探索宇宙的奥秘
the exploration of the universe revealed by science.
是时候再次探险了
It's time to get going again.
这场即将开始的旅行会向我们展示
We're about to begin a journey that will take us
从最微小的到无穷大的
from the infinitesimal to the infinite,
从时间的开始到遥远的未来
from the dawn of time to the distant future.
我们会探索不同的世界和星系
We'll explore galaxies and suns and worlds,
在时间和空间的组合中畅游
surf the gravity waves of space-time,
接触生活在火中和冰中的生物
encounter beings that live in fire and ice,
探索永恒不灭的星系
explore the planets of stars that never die,
了解和恒星一样大的原子
discover atoms as massive as suns
还有比原子还小的宇宙
and universes smaller than atoms.
这也是关于人类的故事
Cosmos is also a story about us.
这也是先人们对星空研究的史诗长篇
It's the saga of how wandering
bands of hunters and gatherers
这也是先人们对星空研究的史诗长篇
found their way to the stars,
众多英雄共同谱写的史诗
one adventure with many heroes.
我们需要想象力来完成这次历险
To make this journey,we'll need imagination.
但仅靠想象力是不够的
But imagination alone is not enough
因为大自然的真实样子是超乎想象的神奇
because the reality of nature is far more wondrous
than anything we can imagine.
几代研究人员的努力使这次的历险成为可能
This adventure is made possible
by generations of searchers
他们严格地坚持一套简单的规则
strictly adhering to a simple set of rules...
以试验和观察结果检验观点
test ideas by experiment and observation,
以通过检验的观点为基础
build on those ideas
that pass the test,
摒弃未通过检验的
reject the ones that fail,
用证据说话
follow the evidence wherever it leads
并对一切存疑
and question everything.
接受这些规则
Accept these terms,
这就是你的宇宙
and the cosmos is yours.
跟我来吧
Now come with me.
中文翻译 @SaltyEggPain
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
在这艘想象之船中
In this ship of the Imagination,
不受空间和时间的限制
free from the shackles of space and time,
我们可以去任何地方
we can go anywhere.
如果你想知道我们身处太空何处
If you want to see where we are in space,
只要看向窗外
just look out the front window.
以时间来说，过去就在我们脚下
In the dimension of time, the past lies beneath us.
这就是地球2.5亿年前的样子
Here's what Earth looked like 250 million years ago.
抬头，就可以看到未来的样子
If you want to see the future, look up.
这就是2.5亿年后可能的样子
And this is how it could appear 250 million years from now.
如果我们要尝试
If we're going to be venturing out
在极度广阔的宇宙中联系
into the farthest reaches of the cosmos,
我们需要知道自己的宇宙地址
we need to know our cosmic address,
这就是我们地址的第一行
and this is the first line of that address.
地球
我们现在离开地球，这个我们仅有的家园
We're leaving the Earth,
the only home we've ever known,
向极度宽广的宇宙进发
for the farthest reaches of the cosmos.
我们最近的邻居，月球，没有大气层
Our nearest neighbor, the Moon, has no sky,
没有海洋，没有生命
no ocean, no life...
只有天体撞击的伤痕
just the scars of cosmic impacts.
太阳为风和浪提供能量
Our star powers the wind and the waves
为地球表面一切的生物提供能量
and all the life on the surface of our world.
整个太阳系都被太阳的引力场所包围
The Sun holds all the worlds of the solar system
从水星开始
in its gravitational embrace, starting with Mercury...
到云层覆盖的金星，失控温室效应
...to cloud-covered Venus,
where runaway greenhouse effect
把它变成一处炼狱
has turned it into a kind of hell.
火星
Mars...
表面积和地球相近
a world with as much land as Earth itself.
一条岩石似的小行星带
A belt of rocky asteroids circles the Sun
在火星和木星的轨道间围绕太阳运行
between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter.
木星被四个大卫星和几十个小卫星环绕
With its four giant moons
and dozens of smaller ones,
木星好像拥有自己的太阳系一般
Jupiter is like its own little solar system.
它的质量超过所有其他行星的总和
It has more mass than
all the other planets combined.
木星的大红斑
Jupiter's Great Red Spot...
它是一个比地球大3倍的古老风暴
a hurricane three times the size of our whole planet
已经存在了几百年之久
that's been raging for centuries.
土星宛如太阳系中皇冠上的明珠
The crown jewel of our solar system, Saturn,
被无数运行轨道和缓慢翻滚的雪球所环绕
ringed by freeways of countless orbiting
and slowly tumbling snowballs...
每个雪球都是一个小月亮
every snowball, a little moon.
天王星
Uranus...
还有海王星
and Neptune,
这颗古人未知的最偏远的行星
the outermost planets,
unknown to the ancients
直到望远镜发明后才被发现
and only discovered after
the invention of the telescope.
在这最偏远的行星之外
Beyond the outermost planet,
还有成千上万的冰冻世界
there's a swarm of tens
of thousands of frozen worlds.
冥王星就是其中一个
And Pluto is one them.
在我们所有的航天器中
Of all our spacecraft,
这是离家最远的一个
this is the one that's traveled
farthest from home...
旅行者1号
Voyager 1.
她承载着我们发向未来的信息
She bears a message to
a billion years from now,
关于我们是谁
something of who we were,
我们的体会
how we felt
以及我们创作的音乐
and the music we made.
浩瀚宇宙海洋中
The deeper waters
更深层的水流里
of this vast cosmic ocean
存在着数不尽的世界
and their numberless worlds lie ahead.
从这里看，太阳好像和其他星星并无两样
From out here, the Sun may look like
just another star.
但它的引力场依然影响着
But it still exerts its gravitational hold
数万亿的冰冻彗星
on a trillion frozen comets,
还有太阳系中那些形成于大约50亿年前的
leftovers from the formation of the solar system
其他所有组成部分
nearly five billion years ago.
我们称之为 奥尔特云
It's called the Oort Cloud.
以前从没有人见过，也不可能见过
No one has ever seen it before,
nor could they,
因为这些天体
because each one of these little worlds
与它最近的邻居之间的距离
is as far from its nearest neighbor
和地球与土星的距离差不多 (12-16亿公里）
as Earth is from Saturn.
这个包含太阳系的巨大彗星云团
This enormous cloud of comets
encloses the solar system,
就是我们宇宙地址的第二行
which is the second line
of our cosmic address.
地球
太阳系
我们有能力探测其他星系的行星
We've only been able to detect
the planets of other stars
也就是最近几十年的事情
for a few decades,
但是我们已经知道行星的数量是很多的
but we already know
that planets are plentiful...
比恒星的数量要多得多
they outnumber the stars.
几乎所有的行星都和地球很不一样
Almost all of them will be very different from Earth,
不适合生物生存
and hostile to life as we know it.
但是我们对于生物又有多少了解呢？
But what do we know about life?
目前我们只接触过一种
We've met only one kind so far.
地球生物
Earthlife.
看到什么了吗？
See anything?
只是空荡荡的太空 对吗
Just empty space, right?
人类的眼睛只能看到
Human eyes see only a sliver of the light
宇宙中得一丝光亮
that shines in the cosmos.
但是科技让我们可以看到肉眼无法看到的
But science gives us the power
to see what our senses cannot.
夜视镜可以让我们看见红外线
Infrared is the kind of light made visible
by night-vision goggles.
向黑暗中发射一个红外感应器
Throw an infrared sensor across the darkness...
流浪行星
Rogue planet.
不绕恒星公转的行星
World without a sun.
我们的银河中有数十亿颗游荡在永恒的黑夜中
Our galaxy has billions of them,
adrift in perpetual night.
在他们原本的星系诞生时的混乱中
They're orphans, cast away
from their mother stars
他们像孤儿一样失去了恒星母亲
during the chaotic birth
of their native star systems.
流浪行星有着熔岩般的内核
Rogue planets are molten at the core
但是冰冻的表面
but frozen at the surface.
在这些极端区域的中间
There may be oceans of liquid water
也许存在着大洋般的液体水
in the zone between those extremes.
谁又能知道水中生活着什么东西呢
Who knows what might be swimming there?
这是银河的红外线显示图
This is what the Milky Way
looks like in infrared.
每个小点，不仅仅是那些明亮的
Every single dot,
not just the bright ones,
都是一颗恒星
is a star.
多少恒星？
How many stars?
多少行星？
How many worlds?
多少中生命存在的方式？
How many ways of being alive?
我们身处图片中的何处？
Where are we in this picture?
看到那条螺旋臂了吗？
See that trailing outer arm?
我们就在那里
That's where we live...
距离中心3万光年
about 30,000 light-years
from the center.
银河系
The Milky Way Galaxy
我们宇宙地址的下一行
is the next line of our cosmic address.
我们现在离家十万光年
We're now a hundred thousand
light-years from home.
光波，存在的速度最快的东西
It would take light,
the fastest thing there is,
要花10万年才能从地球到达我们这里
a hundred thousand years
to reach us from Earth.
这是仙女座螺旋星系
This is the Great Spiral in Andromeda,
银河系的隔壁邻居
the galaxy next door.
我们将这两大星系
We call our two giant galaxies
和一些较小的星系称为
and a smattering of smaller ones
本星系群
the "local group."
地球，太阳系，银河系，本星系群
从这里已经看不到银河系了
Can't even find our home galaxy from out here.
它只是室女座超星系团中得几千份之一
It's just one of thousands
in the Virgo Supercluster.
以这个比例来说
On this scale,
我们所看到的，哪怕最小的点
all the objects we see,
including the tiniest dots,
都是一个星系
are galaxies.
每个星系包含几十亿颗恒星
Each galaxy contains billions of suns
和数不清的行星世界
and countless worlds.
然而，整个室女座超星系团
Yet, the entire Virgo Supercluster itself
只是我们宇宙的一个极小组成部分
forms but a tiny part of our universe.
这是我们已知的最大范围的宇宙
This is the cosmos
on the grandest scale we know...
一张由数以千亿的星系组成的大网
a network of a hundred billion galaxies.
也是我们宇宙地址的最后一行
It's the last line of our cosmic address...
截止目前
for now.
地球，太阳系，银河系，本星系群
室女座超星系团，可观测宇宙
可观测宇宙
Observable universe?!
什么意思
What does that mean?
即使我们在想象之船中
Even for us, in our
Ship of the Imagination,
在时空中所能看到的也是有限的
there's a limit to how far
we can see in space-time.
这是我们的宇宙水平线
It's our cosmic horizon.
一部分的宇宙处于水平线之下
Beyond that horizon
lie parts of the universe
离我们实在太遥远了
that are too far away.
在仅有的时间里
There hasn't been enough time
在宇宙138亿年的历史中
in the 13.8 billion year history of the universe
光线还来不及传递过来
for their light to have reached us.
很多人猜测，所有的这一切
Many of us suspect
that all of this...
所有的行星，恒星，星系，星团
all the worlds, stars,
galaxies and clusters
我们的可观测宇宙中得一切
in our observable universe...
只是其他宇宙中得沧海一粟
is but one tiny bubble in an infinite ocean
of other universes...
多重宇宙论
...a multiverse.
宇宙之上的宇宙
Universe upon universe.
没有尽头的世界
Worlds without end.
感觉很渺小吗
Feeling a little small?
相对宇宙来说 我们确实很渺小
Well, in the context
of the cosmos, we are small.
我们或许只是生活在这浩瀚宇宙中
We may just be little guys
living on a speck of dust,
漂浮的灰尘粒上的小不点
afloat in a staggering immensity,
但我们并不坐井观天
but we don't think small.
现在的宇宙论诞生并不久远
This cosmic perspective is relatively new.
仅仅400年前，我们尚未认识
A mere four centuries ago,
our tiny world was oblivious
自身世界以外的宇宙
to the rest of the cosmos.
那时没有望远镜
There were no telescopes.
只能看到我们肉眼可见的部分
The universe was only what you
could see with the naked eye.
在1599年
Back in 1599,
所有人都认为太阳，行球，星星
everyone knew that the Sun,
planets and stars
只是环绕地球的亮光
were just lights in the sky
that revolved around the Earth,
我们是宇宙的中心
and that we were the center
of a little universe,
由上帝为我们创造的宇宙
a universe made for us.
当时全世界只有一个人
There was only one man
on the whole planet
想象着一个无尽的浩瀚宇宙
who envisioned
an infinitely grander cosmos.
他是怎么度过他的1600年除夕？
And how was he spending
New Year's Eve
他是怎么度过他的1600年除夕？
of the year 1600?
当然是在监狱里
Why, in prison, of course.
生命中总有那么一天
There comes a time in our lives
我们发现自己并不是宇宙的中心
when we first realize we're not
the center of the universe,
我们以外还有更广大的世界
that we belong to something
much greater than ourselves.
这就是成长
It's part of growing up.
每个人都会经历
And as it happens to each of us,
我们的文明也在16世纪经历过这样的成长
so it began to happen to our civilization
in the 16th century.
想象一下望远镜问世之前
Imagine a world before telescopes,
我们只能靠肉眼观察这个宇宙
when the universe
was only what you could see
我们只能靠肉眼观察这个宇宙
with the naked eye.
很显然地球是静止不动的
It was obvious that Earth was motionless,
天空中得一切
and that everything in the heavens...
太阳 月亮 星星 星球
the Sun, the Moon, the stars, the planets...
都围绕着我们运行  然后
revolved around us... and then...
一位名叫哥白尼的波兰天文学家兼牧师
a Polish astronomer and priest named Copernicus
提出一个地球并非中心的激进假想
made a radical proposal.
The Earth was not the center.
地球只是和其他星星一样的行星
It was just one of the planets,
and, like them,
绕着太阳旋转
it revolved around the Sun.
很多人 例如宗教改革发起人马丁·路德
Many, like the Protestant reformer Martin Luther,
认为这是在对圣经的可耻侮辱
took this idea as a scandalous
affront to Scripture.
他们震怒了
They were horrified.
但是另一个人却认为哥白尼说的不全面
But for one man,
Copernicus didn't go far enough.
他叫焦尔达诺·布鲁诺
他生性反叛
and he was a natural-born rebel.
他渴望打破这狭隘宇宙的枷锁
He longed to bust out of that
cramped little universe.
在那不勒斯做道明会的修道士时
Even as a young Dominican monk in Naples,
他就与这个世界格格不入
he was a misfit.
This was a time
当时在意大利没有思想的自由
when there was
no freedom of thought in Italy.
但是布鲁诺渴望了解
But Bruno hungered to know
关于上帝创世的一切
everything about God's creation.
他阅读了被教廷禁止的书籍
He dared to read the books
banned by the Church,
从此踏上了不归路
and that was his undoing.
这些书籍中
In one of them,
有一本作者是1500年前的古罗马人
（物性论 - 卢克莱修）
an ancient Roman, a man dead
for more than 1,500 years
想他描述了一个更广阔的宇宙
whispered to him of a universe far greater,
广阔的犹如他的上帝一般
one as boundless as his idea of God.
卢克莱修让他的读者
Lucretius asked the reader
想象站在宇宙的边缘
to imagine standing
at the edge of the universe
向外射出一支箭
and shooting an arrow outward.
如果箭继续前进，那么很明显
If the arrow keeps going,
then clearly,
宇宙继续向所谓的边缘以外延伸
the universe extends beyond
what you thought was the edge.
但是如果箭不继续前进
But if the arrow doesn't keep going...
比方说 撞在一堵墙上
say it hits a wall...
then that wall must lie
那么墙必然是处在所谓的边缘之外
beyond what you thought
was the edge of the universe.
那么如果你站在这堵墙上向外射箭
Now if you stand on that wall
and shoot another arrow,
也只有这相同的两个结果
there are only the same
two possible outcomes...
要么是飞入无尽的太空
it either flies forever out into space,
要么是撞在某个障碍物上
or it hits some boundary
然后你又可以站在上面射出另一支箭
where you can stand and shoot
yet another arrow.
无论如何 宇宙是没有界限的
Either way, the universe is unbounded.
宇宙必然是无尽的
The cosmos must be infinite.
布鲁诺深以为然
This made perfect sense to Bruno.
他崇拜的上帝是全能的
The God he worshiped was infinite.
所以他断定 上帝创造的宇宙怎会不是无穷
So how, he reasoned, could
Creation be anything less?
那是他的最后一份稳定工作
It was the last steady job he ever had.
后来 当他30岁时
And then, when he was 30,
他的一个幻觉从此改变他的一生
he had the vision that sealed his fate.
在这个梦中 他认识到了
In this dream, he awakened to a world
一个包含在一群行星中的世界
enclosed inside a confining bowl of stars.
就是他那个时代的宇宙
This was the cosmos of Bruno's time.
他感到一阵不舒服的害怕
He experienced a sickening moment of fear,
就像脚下的一切
as if the bottom of everything
向下坠落
was falling away beneath his feet.
但是他鼓起了勇气
But he summoned up his courage.
我展开自信的翅膀飞向太空
I spread confident wings to space
向上高飞至无尽的天空
and soared toward the infinite,
leaving far behind me
将一切的压力抛在身后
what others strained to see
from a distance.
这里没有上 没有下 没有边界
Here, there was no up, no down, no edge,
没有中心
no center.
我看见太阳和其他星星一样
I saw that the Sun
was just another star,
还有其他被行星伴随着的恒星
and the stars were other Suns,
each escorted by other Earths
就像我们的太阳
like our own.
这巨大的启示对他就如同
The revelation of this immensity was like
坠入爱河
falling in love.
布鲁诺变成了一个传教士
Bruno became an evangelist,
他在欧洲各地宣扬他的宇宙无限论
spreading the gospel
of infinity throughout Europe.
他以为其他上帝的追随者会同样接受
He assumed that other lovers
of God would naturally embrace
这个对于创世的伟大并荣耀的观点
this grander and more glorious view of Creation.
我太傻了
What a fool I was.
在他的祖国 他被罗马天主教会开除教籍
He was excommunicated
by the Roman Catholic Church in his homeland,
他不仅被瑞士加尔文长老会驱逐出境
expelled by the Calvinists in Switzerland,
还被德国的路德教派驱逐出境
and by the Lutherans in Germany.
布鲁诺接受了一份邀请
Bruno jumped at an invitation
去英国牛津大学讲课
to lecture at Oxford, in England.
他认为这是一个机会
At last, he thought,
可以与他类似的人分享他的观点
a chance to share his vision
with an audience of his peers.
我来介绍一个对于宇宙的崭新看法
I have come to present
a new vision of the cosmos.
哥白尼是对的
Copernicus was right to argue that our world
我们的世界并不是宇宙的中心
is not the center of the universe.
地球绕着太阳旋转
The Earth goes around the Sun.
它和其他行星一样
It's a planet, just like the others.
但哥白尼只是曙光
But Copernicus was only the dawn.
而我为你们带来日出
I bring you the sunrise.
那些星星和我们炙热的太阳一样
The stars are other fiery suns,
由和地球一样的天体组成
made of the same substance as the Earth,
他们也有自己的含水的地球
and they have their own watery earths,
上面有着和我们一样高贵的动物植物
with plants and animals
no less noble than our own.
你是疯了还是太蠢
Are you mad or merely ignorant?
总所周知只有一个世界
Everyone knows there is only one world.
那是错误的
What everyone knows is wrong.
我们全能的上帝创造了一个无边无际的宇宙
Our infinite God has created
a boundless universe
其中包含了无数的星球
with an infinite number of worlds.
你们那的人没读过亚里斯多德的书吗
Do they not read Aristotle where you come from?
或者是圣经吗
Or even the Bible?
我请求你摒弃老旧和传统的信仰和权威
I beg you, reject antiquity, tradition, faith, and authority.
让我们重新认识
Let us begin anew,
质疑我们以为已经被证实的一切
by doubting everything we assume
异端者
- has been proven.
- Heretic!
异教徒
Infidel!
你们信仰的上帝太小了
Your God is too small.
明智的人本应该从中吸取了教训
A wiser man would have learned his lesson.
可惜布鲁诺并不是那个人
But Bruno was not such a man.
他不停的宣扬自己观点
He couldn't keep his soaring
vision of the cosmos to himself,
尽管这会带来沉痛的代价
despite the fact that the penalty for doing so
在他的那个时代，代价是如此的残酷
in his world was the most vicious form
无情和不寻常的惩罚
of cruel and unusual punishment.
焦尔达诺·布鲁诺生活的那个时代
Giordano Bruno lived at a time when there was no such thing
没有政教分离
as the separation of church and state,
没有言论自由神圣不可侵犯
or the notion that freedom
of speech was a sacred right
没有言论自由神圣不可侵犯
of every individual.
表达与传统信仰相悖的观点
Expressing an idea that didn't
conform to traditional belief
会带来极大的麻烦
could land you in deep trouble.
布鲁诺不顾一切地回到了意大利
Recklessly, Bruno returned to Italy.
也许是想家了
Maybe he was homesick.
可是他必须知道
But still, he must have known
that his homeland
他的祖国对他来说
was one of the most dangerous
places in Europe
是最危险的国家
he could possibly go.
由罗马天主教会管辖的宗教法庭
The Roman Catholic Church
maintained a system of courts
被称为异端裁判所
known as the Inquisition,
它唯一职责就是审查和折磨
and its sole purpose was to investigate and torment
与教会持有不同声音和观点的人
anyone who dared voice views that differed from theirs.
布鲁诺很快就被思想警察抓获
It wasn't long before Bruno fell into the clutches
of the thought police.
这位信奉无限宇宙的流浪者
This wanderer, who worshiped
an infinite universe,
在八年的监狱生涯中饱受煎熬
languished in confinement for eight years.
尽管受尽残酷的审讯
Through relentless interrogations,
他依然不愿放弃他的观点
he stubbornly refused to renounce his views.
为什么教会要花
Why was the Church willing
如此长的时间来折磨布鲁诺
to go to such lengths to torment Bruno?
他们在害怕什么
What were they afraid of?
如果布鲁诺是对的 那么这些圣典
If Bruno was right, then the sacred books
还有教会的权威
and the authority of the Church
都会受到质疑
would be open to question.
最终 异端裁判所的红衣主教们
Finally, the cardinals of the Inquisition
做出了他们的判决
rendered their verdict.
你有罪
You are found guilty
你质疑圣父圣子圣灵三位一体
of questioning the Holy Trinity
你质疑耶稣基督的神威
and the divinity of Jesus Christ.
你相信上帝的怒火不会永远
Of believing that God's wrath is not eternal,
所有人都会被宽恕
that everyone will be saved.
你断言其他世界存在的主张
Of asserting the existence of other worlds.
你写的所有书
All of the books you have written
都会在圣彼得广场前焚毁
will be gathered up and burned in St. Peter's Square.
尊敬的大人 8年的监禁
Reverend Father, these eight years of confinement
给了我很多时间去反省
have given me much time to reflect.
然后呢
So...
你要放弃你的主张吗
you will recant?
我对造物主的爱和崇敬
My love and reverence for the Creator
激发我对全能的上帝的认识
inspires in me the vision of an infinite Creation.
你会被移交到罗马总督
You shall be turned over to the Governor of Rome
予以执行相应地惩罚
to administer the appropriate punishment
如果你拒不忏悔的话
for those who will not repent.
可能你宣布这个判决时的恐惧
It may be that you are more afraid
比我听到判决的时候更厉害
to deliver this judgment than I am to hear it.
布鲁诺殉难的10年后
Ten years after Bruno's martyrdom,
伽利略通过望远镜
Galileo first looked through a telescope,
发现布鲁诺的学说确实没错
realizing that Bruno had been right all along.
银河系是由肉眼看不到的无数恒星组成
The Milky Way was made of countless stars
invisible to the naked eye,
天空中的某些光亮其实是其他的行星
and some of those lights in the
sky were actually other worlds.
布鲁诺不是科学家
Bruno was no scientist.
他只是侥幸猜中了
His vision of the cosmos was a lucky guess,
因为没有证据支持他
because he had no evidence to support it.
就和其他猜想一样 也有可能不对
Like most guesses, it could
well have turned out wrong.
但是这个观点一旦散播出去
But once the idea was in the air,
它就给了其他人一个方向
it gave others a target to aim at.
哪怕只是为了反驳
If only to disprove it.
布鲁诺大致理解了太空的浩瀚无垠
Bruno glimpsed the vastness of space.
但他对于时间的惊人无际没有丝毫概念
But he had no inkling of the
staggering immensity of time.
寿命很少超过一个世纪的普通人
How can we humans, who rarely
live more than a century,
怎么可能去理解宇宙的历史
hope to grasp the vast expanse of time
就像浩瀚宽阔的时间长河
that is the history of the cosmos?
宇宙诞生于138亿年前
The universe is 13.8 thousand million years old.
为了更好地想象宇宙的历史
In order to imagine all of cosmic time,
我们把它压缩成12个月的年历
let's compress it into a single calendar year.
年历上的1月1号是宇宙诞生的日子
The cosmic calendar begins on January 1st
with the birth of our universe.
年历上包含了从那以后经历的所有时间
It contains everything that's
happened since then,
一直到现在
up to now,
在这个年历上的12月31号午夜
which on this calendar
is midnight December 31st.
按照这个比例 每个月代表10亿年
On this scale, every month
represents about a billion years.
每天代表将就4千万年
Every day represents nearly 40 million years.
让我们尽可能地回到过去
Let's go back as far as we can,
回到宇宙最开始的时刻
to the very first moment of the universe.
1月1号 宇宙大爆炸
January 1st, the Big Bang.
这是我们所能看到最早的时间
It's as far back as we can see in time...
目前而言
for now.
整个宇宙形成于一个比原子还小的点
Our entire universe emerged from
a point smaller than a single atom.
空间在密度极大温度极高的状态下爆炸
Space itself exploded in a cosmic fire,
由此开始了宇宙的扩张
launching the expansion of the universe
并诞生了所有的能量
and giving birth to all the energy
已经产生所有我们已知的事物
and all the matter we know today.
听上去很疯狂
I know that sounds crazy,
但是我们有很强力的观测证据
but there's strong observational evidence
来支持宇宙大爆炸理论
to support the Big Bang theory.
证据还有氦元素在宇宙中的比例
And it includes the amount
of helium in the cosmos
以及爆炸残留的发光无线电频谱
and the glow of radio waves
left over from the explosion.
爆炸后宇宙开始冷却
As it expanded, the universe cooled,
其间有2亿年左右的黑暗
and there was darkness
for about 200 million years.
万有引力将气体集聚并且加热
Gravity was pulling together
clumps of gas and heating them
直到第一批恒星发出亮光
until the first stars burst into light
相当于1月10号
on January 10th.
1月13号 这些恒星开始结合
On January 13th, these stars coalesced
形成第一批小星系
into the first small galaxies.
这些星系融合成更大的星系
These galaxies merged to form still larger ones,
包括我们的银河系
including our own Milky Way,
产生于110亿年左右
which formed about 11 billion years ago,
就是宇宙年历上得3月15号
on March 15th of the cosmic year.
数千亿的恒星中
Hundreds of billions of suns.
哪个是我们的太阳
Which one is ours?
此时尚未诞生
It's not yet born.
它将从其他恒星的灰烬中产生
It will rise from the ashes of other stars.
看到这些犹如闪光灯般的亮光吗
See those lights flashing like paparazzi?
每一个都是超新星
Each one is a supernova,
一颗超大恒星的耀眼爆炸
the blazing death of a giant star.
恒星消亡和诞生的地方
Stars die and are born
in places like this one...
我们称为星星苗圃 （分子云）
a stellar nursery.
他们像雨滴般
They condense like raindrops
从巨大的气态和灰尘云中凝结
from giant clouds of gas and dust.
他们温度高的可以把原子中的原子核
They get so hot that the nuclei of the atoms
融合在一起
fuse together deep within them
从而产生了我们呼吸的氧气 肌肉中的碳元素
to make the oxygen we breathe,
the carbon in our muscles,
骨头中的钙元素 血中的铁元素
the calcium in our bones,
the iron in our blood,
所有的这一切都产生于
all of it was cooked
从此消亡的恒星炙热的内心
in the fiery hearts of long-vanished stars.
你 我 所有人
You, me, everyone...
我们都是由星辰物质组成
we are made of star stuff.
星辰物质被不断循环和浓缩
This star stuff is recycled and enriched,
一遍又一遍
again and again,
经过几代恒星的诞生消亡
through succeeding generations of stars.
离我们的太阳诞生还有多久
How much longer until the birth of our Sun?
很长时间
A long time.
我们太阳的第一次发光
It won't begin to shine
还要再等60亿年
for another six billion years.
太阳的生日是8月31号
Our Sun's birthday is August 31st
在这个宇宙年历上
on the Cosmic Calendar...
45亿年前
...four and a half billion years ago.
就像太阳系中其他行星
As with the other worlds of our solar system,
地球在一堆气体和灰尘中产生
Earth was formed from a disk of gas and dust
绕着新生的太阳运行
orbiting the newborn Sun.
反复的碰撞产生了一个发光的球状碎片
Repeated collisions produced
a growing ball of debris.
看到那个小行星了吗
See that asteroid?
不是那个
No, not that one.
那边的那个
The one over there.
我们的存在归功于它旁边的引力
We exist because the gravity
of that one next to it
把它轻轻向左推了一英寸
just nudged it an inch to the left.
一英寸有很大的区别吗
What difference could an inch make
按照太阳系的比例来说
on the scale the solar system?
稍等 你马上就能看到
Just wait, you'll see.
在最初的10亿年里
The Earth took one hell of a beating
地球饱受摧残
in its first billion years.
任由轨道上的碎片撞击和融合
Fragments of orbiting debris collided and coalesced,
直到他们形成了我们的月亮
until they snowballed to form our Moon.
月亮是那个暴力纪元的纪念品
The Moon is a souvenir of that violent epoch.
如果你站在远古地球的表面
If you stood on the surface
of that long ago Earth,
月亮会看上去比现在亮100倍
the Moon would have looked
a hundred times brighter.
那时月亮离我们近10倍
It was ten times closer back then,
被比现在更强大的引力场吸引着
locked in a much more intimate
gravitational embrace.
地球冷却下来 海洋形成了
As the Earth cooled, seas began to form.
海浪比现在高1000倍
The tides were a thousand times higher then.
经过极漫长的时间 潮汐的摩擦力
Over the eons,
tidal friction within Earth
将月球推远
pushed the Moon away.
生命差不多在这个时候诞生
Life began somewhere around here,
9月21号
September 21st,
在地球上的35亿年前
three and a half billion
years ago on our little world.
我们依然不知道生命如何起源
We still don't know how life got started.
我们只是知道
For all we know,
有可能是来自银河系的其他地方
it may have come from
another part of the Milky Way.
生命的起源
The origin of life
是最伟大的未知科学奇迹之一
is one of the greatest
unsolved mysteries of science.
生命的演变
That's life cooking,
一切生物化学的进化
evolving all the biochemical recipes
充满了无与伦比的复杂活动
for its incredibly complex activities.
到了11月9号 生命开始呼吸 移动
By November 9th,
life was breathing, moving,
进食和对周遭环境做出反应
eating, responding to its environment.
多亏了这些有开拓性的微生物
We owe a lot to those pioneering microbes.
没错 就是这些不起眼的家伙
Oh, yeah... one other thing.
他们还发明了繁殖
They also invented sex.
12月17号 很特别的一天
December 17th was quite a day.
海洋中生命的发展开始腾飞
Life in the sea really took off,
形形色色的大型植物和动物
it was exploding with a diversity
爆炸式的发展
of larger plants and animals.
提塔利克鱼是最早冒险登陆的动物之一
Tiktaalik was one of the first
animals to venture onto land.
感觉肯定像是造访另一个星球
It must have felt like visiting another planet.
森林  恐龙
Forests, dinosaurs,
鸟类 昆虫
birds, insects,
都在12月的最后一周进化而来
they all evolved in the final week of December.
第一朵花
The first flower...
在12月28号 盛开
bloomed on December 28th.
随着古森林的成长死亡
As these ancient forests grew and died
并被深埋进地下
and sank beneath the surface,
他们的残骸形成了煤
their remains transformed into coal.
3亿年后
300 million years later,
人类燃烧这些煤来推动文明的发展
we humans are burning most of that coal to power
同时也使我们的文明陷入危机
and imperil our civilization.
还记得那颗在太阳系形成时的
Remember that asteroid back in the formation
小行星吗
of the solar system...
那颗被轻轻推动的小行星
the one that got nudged a little to the left?
它来了
Well, here it comes.
早晨6点24分
It's 6:24 AM
宇宙年历上的12月30号
on December 30th on the Cosmic Calendar.
在1亿年的时间里
For more than a hundred million years,
恐龙曾是这个地球的统治者
the dinosaurs were lords of the Earth,
当我们的祖先 小型哺乳动物
while our ancestors, small mammals,
战战兢兢地在地面爬来爬去的时候
scurried fearfully underfoot.
这颗小行星改变了一切
The asteroid changed all that.
假如它没有被推动
Suppose it hadn't been nudged at all.
它会完全和地球擦肩而过
It would have missed the Earth entirely,
恐龙恐怕依然存在
and for all we know, the
dinosaurs might still be here
但我们不会
but we wouldn't.
这是极端突发状况的好例子
This is a good example of the extreme contingency,
生存的偶然性
the chance nature, of existence.
宇宙已经诞生了超过
The universe is already more than 13 and a half
135亿年
billion years old.
人类仍未出现
Still no sign of us.
在这个年历代表的时间长河中
In the vast ocean of time that this calendar represents,
人类在最后一小时进化
we humans only evolved within the last hour
宇宙年历中的最后一天
of the last day of the cosmic year.
11点59分46秒
11:59 and 46 seconds.
全部有记载的历史发生在最后的14秒里
All of recorded history occupies only the last 14 seconds,
你听说过得所有人
and every person you've ever heard of
存在于这个点的某个位置
lived somewhere in there.
所有这些国王 战役 迁徙 发明
All those kings and battles,
migrations and inventions,
战争和爱情 历史书中的一切
wars and loves, everything in the history books
都发生在这宇宙年历中的最后几秒
happened here, in the last seconds
of the Cosmic Calendar.
但如果我们想要研究
But if we want to explore
宇宙年历中这段极短的时间
such a brief moment of cosmic time...
我们必须改变比例
...we'll have to change scale.
我们是这个宇宙的新丁
We are newcomers to the cosmos.
我们的历史仅仅从宇宙年的最后一晚开始
Our own story only begins on the
last night of the cosmic year.
新年前夜的9点45分
It's 9:45 on New Year's Eve.
350万年前
Three and a half million years ago,
你我的祖先留下这些足迹
our ancestors, yours and mine, left these traces.
我们站了起来和他们区别开来
We stood up, and parted ways from them.
自从我们直立行走
Once we were standing on two feet,
我们的双眼不在迷恋地面
our eyes were no longer fixated on the ground.
现在我们可以自由的探索奇迹
Now we were free to look up in wonder.
人类存在的大部分时间里
For the longest part of human existence,
比方说最近的4万代人
say the last 40,000 generations,
我们曾是流浪者
we were wanderers,
猎人和采集者混住在一起
living in small bands of hunters and gatherers,
制作工具 生火
making tools, controlling fire,
给事物起名字
naming things,
都发生在宇宙年历的最后一个小时里
all within the last hour of the Cosmic Calendar.
我们必须改变比例去继续探寻
To find out what happens next, we'll have to change scale
最后一晚的最后一分钟
to see the last minute of the last night
发生了什么
of the cosmic year.
11:59
以宇宙时间比例来说我们太太太年轻了
We're so very young on the time scale of the universe
我们甚至还没开始画出第一张画
that we didn't start painting our first pictures
直到宇宙年历的最后60秒
until the last 60 seconds of the cosmic year,
只不过是3万年前
a mere 30,000 years ago.
我们发明了天文学
This is when we invented astronomy.
事实上我们都是天文学家的后裔
In fact, we're all descended from astronomers.
我们的生存要依靠研究星星
Our survival depended on
knowing how to read the stars
用来预测冬天的到来
in order to predict the coming of the winter
以及兽群的迁徙
and the migration of the wild herds.
然后大约1万年前
And then, around 10,000 years ago,
我们的生活方式迎来了变革
there began a revolution in the way we lived.
我们的祖先学会了如何改变周围环境
Our ancestors learned
how to shape their environment,
栽培植物 驯养动物
taming wild plants and animals,
耕作土地 定居下来
cultivating land and settling down.
这改变了一切
This changed everything.
有史以来第一次
For the first time in our history,
我们可以拥有超过我们负重能力的东西
we had more stuff than we could carry.
我们需要把这些数量记录下来
We needed a way to keep track of it.
午夜前的14秒
At 14 seconds to midnight,
大约6千年前 我们发明了书写
or about 6,000 years ago, we invented writing.
随后不久我们就开始记录其他东西
And it wasn't long before we started recording
不仅仅是粮食的数量
more than bushels of grain.
书写让我们保存我们的想法
Writing allowed us to save our thoughts
并且跨越时间和空间的传播它们
and send them much further in space and time.
泥板上的细小印记
Tiny markings on a clay tablet
成了我们征服有限的生命的手段
became a means for us to vanquish mortality.
震撼了整个世界
It shook the world.
摩西出生于7秒之前
Moses was born seven seconds ago.
释迦摩尼 6秒前
Buddha, six seconds ago.
耶稣基督 5秒前
Jesus, five seconds ago.
穆罕穆德 3秒前
Mohammed, three seconds ago.
不到2秒前 不论好坏
It was not even two seconds ago that, for better or worse,
地球一边的人类发现了地球的另一边
the two halves of the Earth discovered each other.
仅仅在最后的一秒钟里
And it was only in the very last second
我们开始使用科学
of the Cosmic Calendar that we began to use science
去揭示大自然的秘密和规则
to reveal nature's secrets and her laws.
科学方法是如此的强大
The scientific method is so powerful
只用了4个世纪的时间
that in a mere four centuries,
就从伽利略第一次看向望远镜
it has taken us from Galileo's first look through a telescope
到人类在月球上留下足迹
at another world to leaving our footprints on the Moon.
它让我们可以越过时间和空间
It allowed us to look out across space and time
去观察我们在宇宙时空中的位置
to discover where and when we are in the cosmos.
我们有了了解宇宙本质的办法
We are a way for the cosmos to know itself.
卡尔赛根30多年前带领我们进行了首次的
Carl Sagan guided the maiden voyage of Cosmos
宇宙航行
a generation ago.
他不仅是20世纪最成功的
He was the most successful
science communicator
科学传播者
of the 20th century,
也是一位首屈一指的科学家
but he was first and foremost a scientist.
卡尔为我们了解行星
Carl contributed enormously
做出了极大的贡献
to our knowledge of the planets.
他正确地预测了有沼气湖存在于
He correctly predicted the existence of methane lakes
木星的卫星 泰坦 土卫六上
on Saturn's giant moon Titan.
他指出早期地球的大气层中
He showed that the atmosphere of the early Earth
必然含有强大的温室气体
must have contained powerful greenhouse gases.
他首先推断出火星上的季节变化
He was the first to understand
that seasonal changes on Mars
是由沙尘暴引起
were due to windblown dust.
卡尔是一位
Carl was a pioneer
在探索地球以外智慧生物领域的
in the search for extraterrestrial life
先行者
and intelligence.
太空时代的最初40年里 每次主要的
He played a leading role in
every major spacecraft mission
太阳系探索航天任务 他都担任了
to explore the solar system during the first 40 years
重要的职务
of the Space Age.
这还不是全部
But that's not all he did.
这是卡尔的一本1975年的记事日历
This is Carl Sagan's own calendar from 1975.
我那时在做什么
Who was I back then?
我只是一个纽约的17岁男孩
I was just a 17-year-old kid from the Bronx
梦想着可以成为科学家
with dreams of becoming a scientist,
世界上最著名的天文学家
and somehow the world's most
famous astronomer found time
邀请我去纽约州
to invite me to Ithaca, in upstate New York,
和他共度一个周六
and spend a Saturday with him.
我记得那天下着雪
I remember that snowy day like it was yesterday.
他来公车站接我
He met me at the bus stop
带我参观了他在康奈尔大学的实验室
and showed me his laboratory at Cornell University.
卡尔从书桌后拿出这本书并在上面为我题字
Carl reached behind his desk
and inscribed this book for me.
至 尼尔 未来的天文学家
"For Neil, a future astronomer.
卡尔
Carl."
结束后 他开车送我去公车站
At the end of the day, he drove
me back to the bus station.
雪下得更大了
The snow was falling harder.
他写下他的电话号码 家里的电话
He wrote his phone number...
his home phone number...
他把号码写在一张小纸片上 如果公车没有来
on a scrap of paper and he said,
"If the bus can't get through,
打电话给我 就在我家过夜
call me and spend the night at my home with my family."
我当时已经决定要当一名科学家
I already knew I wanted to become a scientist,
但是那天下午 我认识到
but that afternoon, I learned from Carl
我要做他那样的人
the kind of person I wanted to become.
他帮助了我 还有其他很多人
He reached out to me and to countless others,
激励我们去学习，教授，研究科学
inspiring so many of us to study, teach and do science.
科学研究是一份需要合作的事业
Science is a cooperative enterprise,
持续几代人的时间
spanning the generations.
火炬在老师和学生的手中传递
It's the passing of a torch from
teacher to student to teacher,
一群伟大的思想从远古
a community of minds
reaching back to antiquity
贯穿 直至未来的星空
and forward to the stars.
现在跟我来
Now, come with me.
我们的旅程开始了
Our journey is just beginning.
中文翻译 @SaltyEggPain
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com